Chris: Conclusions from the use
of coding principles and practices
Following coding principles will help developer
teams to reduce dependencies, and make designs
easier to understand, maintain and extend.
This helps developers to build adaptive, effective software
which would also be in line with Agile methodology.
However, following coding principles can extend the
design process and make development more difficult, and
it can be seen as a tedious task by some developers.
Leah: As the intention of the principles is to make
code more readable, easier to understand, easier to
test and maintain; most developer teams will consider
the effort and extra time to implement them a valuable
exercise, as this will help to avoid issues that
could occur from not following them at a later date.
So let’s look at some of the principles we have already
discussed and how they can affect code starting with KISS.
Chris: As we discussed in the previous video
the main rule with KISS is that the code
should be simple and therefore easy to modify.
By keeping the programming simple, service and
maintenance are much easier, problems are solved
quicker, the code is deliberately concise, and it
is easier to understand, extend, change, and reuse.
Now let’s consider SOLID
Leah: S - The Single Responsibility
Principle [SRP] title on screen
Good practice of SRP makes code easier to test and
maintain and will prevent side-effects from future
changes, making the software easier to implement.
Chris: O – Open / Closed Principle [OCP] title on screen
Good practice of OCP makes code that is easy
to maintain and revise as you can add new
functionality without changing the existing code.
This is useful in agile methodologies as
stakeholders’ requirements are likely to change.
Leah: L – Liskov Substitution
Principle [LSP] title on screen
Good practice of LSP helps to avoid unexpected
consequences of changes, avoids having to open a closed
class, avoids issues that could occur during updates
and extensions, and allows easy extensions of software.
Chris: I – Interface Segregation
Principle [ISP] title on screen
With ISP as the developers would be focused on
their own client specific interface, they are not
forced to depend on interfaces that they do not use.
This would save the developer time and
increase their motivation and focus.
Leah: D – Dependency Inversion
Principle [DIP] title on screen
As high-level modules [which sustain complex systems] are
not affected by low-level modules [which provide utility
features] with DIP; this premise would speed up development
and make it easier to develop and update the code.
Chris: So, in conclusion using good coding practices
and principles can help create better and more organised
workflow, increased efficiency and productivity,
enhanced product quality and subsequently reduced costs.
Also using coding practices and principles to
avoid the frustration that comes with bugs and
errors should be motivation enough in itself.